# Ryan Wood

I enjoy using my passion and talent to build strikingly simple web applications using Ruby on Rails and an open source software stack.

404 Barley Mill Drive Greer, SC 29651 m 864.517.0030 h 864.335.9592 rvan.wood@gmail.com

blog.ryanwood.com github.com/ryanwood www.linkedin.com/in/ryanwood twitter.com/ryanwood

# **Technology Skills**

Below are the technologies in which I am extremely competent:

**Development:** Ruby, Ruby on Rails, JavaScript (jQuery), too many gems to name...

Presentation: Clean, well organized standards-based web development: (X)HTML, HTML5, CSS2/3,

Haml/Sass. AJAX used where appropriate for speed or usability.

Stack: Ubuntu Linux, Nginx or Apache, Passenger, Sinatra, Mongrel, Thin, Heroku

Tools: Macbook Pro, TextMate, VIM, Git (and Subversion), Pivotal Tracker, Fogbugz

Data: PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, MongoDB, CouchDB, Microsoft SQL Server

Expert in relational database design, data modeling & data normalization.

Process: Agile, iterative development in short iterations. Embrace change. Test everything

(RSpec, Shoulda, Test::Unit). Extensive Scrum experience.

Style: Huge believer in open source software. Contributed to many open source projects

and have a few of my own. See github.com/ryanwood for details.

# Beyond the Technology

While technical skills are incredibly important, a fit with a company's mission, style, and people are critical for a successful working relationship. Here is a little more about me, the guy you'd be working with day in and day out.

I am highly inquisitive, creative, and resourceful. Since I tend to be a perfectionist in my work, I nearly always deliver well beyond expectations. I have a knack for hitting the ground running with new technologies, learning them quickly, and translating those technologies into valuable business solutions. I am constantly learning.

Coding is an art form. My emphasis on logic and organization in code is balanced by my desire to experience joy while reading it. Beautiful code is better code.

My communication and collaboration skills have been honed by my background as a counselor. I find that experience helps me to be an effective team member and a better leader.

# **Work History**

#### **Chief Technical Officer**

Weddzilla, LLC (McLean, VA)

April 2010-Present

Weddzilla is a boot-strapped start up focused on bringing together brides and vendors in the wedding space. It strives to be the leader in social wedding planning with a high emphasis on leveraging existing social networks. I joined Weddzilla as the CTO to lead architecture, development, and streamline the development process. The product is built entirely with Ruby on Rails, Postgresql and deployed to Heroku. Though I am responsible for "all things technical", I wear many hats and spend much of my time in the trenches coding. Responsibilities include:

- Running a geographically remote development team using an iterative development process
- Coordinating the product vision, architecture and design
- Managing the full lifecycle development process of a large scale Rails implementation

#### Consultant, Owner & President

Sourcescape (Greenville, SC)

May 1999-Present

Over the past 10 years, I have developed numerous web-based applications in a variety of languages and platforms. Since 2005, I have focused exclusively on building solutions using Ruby on Rails. Some featured projects include:

- A social wedding planning site for <u>Weddzilla</u>
- Centralized lead management system for <u>The JCA Company Publishers</u>
- Inventory management system for <u>Olympus Printing & Graphic</u>
- Human Resources processing application for <u>Benefit Resources</u>

#### **Senior Software Architect**

First Data Corporation (Greenville, SC)

July 2006-October 2009

As the chief architect of the collection platform for <u>TeleCheck</u> (a First Data subsidiary), I was responsible for all architectural decisions, development, development process, and code delivery. I also participated as a lead developer and mentor to the development team. Other responsibilities include:

- Increased productivity and efficiency by architecting and building TeleCheck's next generation collection application. Leveraging a team of on-site and off shore developers to move their business from multiple green screen terminals to a portal based web application.
- Saving First Data hundreds of development hours, I created Slither, a DSL for describing and parsing fixed-width text files, and released it as an open source Ruby gem for community use
- Eliminated 20+ hours of weekly manual work by building Ruby applications to automate complex integrations with various consolidation banks
- Managed development teams in Greenville and India using a Scrum-based agile process
- Established best practices and development standards by coaching the team
- Administered development systems including bug tracking (Fogbugz), SCM (Subversion, Git) and a custom build and deployment process developed in Ruby

### MIS Development Manager, Lead Architect & Developer

Infor, formerly Datastream Systems, Inc. (Greenville, SC) January 2003-July 2006

I was responsible for the successful project management, architecture and development of all MIS development projects. I did much of the hands-on development as well as mentor the rest of the team on successful development strategies and processes.

- Developed internal best practices and standards
- Implemented an adapted agile project management system (combining aspects of Scrum and Extreme Programming) to remain flexible and efficient in the development process
- Headed the development team that built a custom front-end for a workflow engine (BizFlow) to handle the employee entrance, transfer, & exit using ASP.NET(C#), .NET Web Services, XML, & custom SOAP integration
- Built custom commission management system used by Datastream using SQL Server 2000 Reporting Services, Windows Forms for administration, and SQL 2000 back-end
- Created a corporate goal tracking application in ASP.NET (C#) & SQL Server 2000 which enables executives to monitor progress toward corporate goals & objectives
- Founded and facilitated a semi-weekly "Lunch & Learn" to provide in-house training and mentoring on .NET, object oriented techniques, & application development strategies

#### Senior Web Application Developer

Infor, formerly Datastream Systems, Inc. (Greenville, SC) October 1999-December 2002

In this role, I was responsible for designing and building enterprise web-based applications. I also functioned as the lead data architect and database designer for SQL Server.

- Led the complete re-design and infrastructure development of the portal-based Datastream Corporate Intranet (over 800 users) using ColdFusion, JavaScript, & SQL Server
- Created a sales forecasting application in ColdFusion allowing executives, managers, and the sales team to see the sales pipeline up to 18 months in advance
- Developed a web-based sales tracking system using ASP and SQL Server that provides the Datastream sales force and managers with up to the minute sales reports
- Innovated the development process by introducing source control, specific coding methodologies (Fusebox), and internal development standards (documentation)

#### **Database Development Consultant**

**GE Power Systems** (Greenville, SC)

February 1999-October 1999

As a consultant at GE I worked in the Finance Department to develop custom database applications that streamlined Gas Turbine cost estimations.

- Built CERA (Cost Estimate Reporting Application), an Access-based Reporting Application for the GE Finance Department. All data was pulled and manipulated from Mainframe and Sybase
- Designed and developed solutions using Microsoft Access which are responsible for cost tracking for over \$1.5 Billion of equipment
- Increased finance team effectiveness by transforming a process that previously took weeks to less than 30 minutes

#### **Major Accounts Billing Analyst**

IKON Office Solutions (Orlando, FL)

May 1998-February 1999

As a major account analyst I managed the billing process for multi-million dollar accounts and worked with sales people to ensure that billing issues were resolved smoothly.

- Utilized Access, SQL and VBA to develop and administer complex databases to monitor inventory, generate invoices, and produce reports for major accounts
- Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of a statewide asset tracking database for defaulted leases and unrecovered equipment
- Reduced billing time for the Dade County School Board and Brevard County Commissioner's Office just under a month to less than a day

#### **Program Counselor**

Associated Counseling & Education (Orlando, FL) May 1997-May 1998

- Conducted individual, family, and group counseling sessions
- Taught substance abuse related classes to large and small groups
- Supervised and instructed multiple paraprofessional counselors

#### Education

M.A. in Counseling, May 1997 Reformed Theological Seminary (Orlando, FL)

B.A. in Philosophy and Theology, May 1993 Wheaton College (Wheaton, IL)

# **Organizations**

Founder & Organizer, Upstate Ruby Brigade (upstaterb.org)

Affiliate Member, Greenville Spartanburg Anderson Technology Council (gsatc.org)

#### Certifications

Microsoft Certified Professional (ASP.NET using C#), *Microsoft Corporation*, *January 2003* Certified Advanced ColdFusion Developer, *Macromedia*, *November 2001* 

Last modified: July 2010